Rasool Sharifi

▲ 434-249-3650
➡ arasool.sh2000@gmail.com rasool-sharifi.github.io/
♠ github.com/danteisalive

Overview

My interests lie broadly in Computer Architecture and Domain-Specific Compilers. I am interested in exploring new optimization techniques to enhance the performance, energy efficiency, and programmability of AI accelerators.

•Highlights of my work experience: As a Machine Learning Performance Architect at d-Matrix.ai, my primary responsibilities involved optimizing and enhancing the performance of machine learning models on Corsair hardware. I collaborated closely with the compiler team to comprehend both the model algorithms and the hardware pipeline, which helped in identifying new optimization opportunities. My duties included developing Speed of Light (SOL) simulation models to profile the performance of Large Language Models on Corsair systems, identifying performance bottlenecks, and conducting experiments to test various optimization techniques.

Work Experience

NVIDIA, California, USA,

June. 2024 - August. 2024

Deep Learning Performance Architect - Intern

d-Matrix.ai, California, USA,

May. 2023 - August. 2023

ML Performance Architect - Intern

Responsibilities:

- Developed a python-based pipeline for modeling collective operations
- Developed a python-based pipeline for roofline performance analysis of Large Language Model workloads

d-Matrix.ai, California, USA,

June. 2022 - Dec. 2022

ML Performance Architect - Intern

Responsibilities:

- Performance modeling, correlation, and projection
- Maintaining tools for high-level system simulation of Corsair systems
- · Developed a MLIR compiler pipeline for direct performance evaluation of MLIR workloads

Notable Projects

Optimizing Layout Assignments: A Collaborative Approach with Graph Neural Networks and Large Language Models,

Language: Python, Frameworks: Pytorch, JAX, Torch Geometrics (PyG)

 $\underline{\textbf{Links}} : \texttt{https://github.com/danteisalive/tpugraph} \text{ (will be publicly available after publication)}$

Design and Implementation of MLIR-Based Pipeline for d-Matrix.ai Corsair Performance and Power Projection,

<u>Language</u>: *Python, C++*, <u>Platform</u>: *MLIR, Lark* <u>Links</u>: Part of the internship at d-Matrix.ai

Automatic Resource-aware Generation of Energy-efficient CNN Inference Accelerator for Edge Embedded FPGAs,

Language: C, C++, Chisel, Verilog, Platform: Xilinx Zynq SoC

Links: https://bitbucket.org/alijahan/bnn-pynq/src/master/

Speculation-Driven Dynamic Binary Optimization,

Language: C++, Python, Framework: GEM5

Links: https://github.com/logangregorym/gem5-changes

Compiler for Tiny AVR Microcontrollers,

Language: Java, Platform: Atmel AVR

 $\underline{\textbf{Links}}\text{: https://github.com/danteisalive/AVRCompiler}$

Architecture Support for Memory and Type Safety, Language: C++, Python, Framework: LLVM, GEM5, Pin

Links: https://github.com/danteisalive/llvm-typecheking

 $\underline{\textbf{Links}} \colon \texttt{https://github.com/danteisalive/gem5-tc}$

Links: https://github.com/danteisalive/typetracking_pin

Processing in Memory for Bioinformatics Applications,

Language: C++, Python, Framework: DRAMSim3
Links: https://github.com/umd-memsys/DRAMsim3

Education

University of South Carolina, Columbia, USA (Incomplete)	Jan. 2023 - May. 2024
Ph.D., Computer Science University of Virginia, Charlottesville, USA	Sep. 2018 - Dec. 2022
Ph.D., Computer Science (Transferred to UoSC on Dec. 2022)	
University of Tehran, Tehran, Iran M.Sc., Electronics-Circuit and Systems	Sep. 2013 - June 2016
Isfahan University of Technology, Isfahan, Iran B.Sc., Electrical Engineering	Sep. 2009 - June 2013

Research Experience

University of South Carolina, Columbia, USA,	Jan. 2023 - Present
Graduate Research Assistant	
University of Virginia, Charlottesville, USA,	Sep. 2018 - Dec. 2022
Graduate Research Assistant	
University of Tehran, Tehran, Iran,	Sep. 2013 - June 2016
Graduate Research Assistant	

Publications

- K. Skadron, M. Lenjani, Rasool Sharift, and L. Wu, "Scalable in situ dram-based accelerators and methods of operating the same," US Patent, 2023
- Lingxi Wu, Rahul Sreekumar, Rasool Sharifi, Mircea Stan, Kevin Skadron, and Ashish Venkat, "Hardware Trojans in eNVM Neuromorphic Devices," in Design, Automation and Test in Europe Conference, 2023. Nominated for Best Paper Award
- Logan Moody, Wei Qi, Rasool Sharifi, Layne Berry, Joey Rudek, Sreenivas Subramoney, Jayesh Gaur, Jeff Parkhurst, Kevin Skadron, and Ashish Venkat, "Speculative Code Compaction: Eliminating Dead Code via Speculative Microcode Transformations," in *IEEE/ACM 53rd International Symposium on Microarchitecture (MICRO)*, 2022
- L. Wu, Rasool Sharifi, A. Venkat, and K. Skadron, "Dram-cam: General-purpose bit-serial exact pattern matching," *IEEE Computer Architecture Letters (CAL)*, 2022
- Lingxi Wu, Rasool Sharifi, Marzieh Lenjani, Kevin Skadron, and Ashish Venkat, "Sieve: A Scalable In-Situ DRAM-based Accelerator for Massively Parallel K-mer Matching," in 2021 ACM/IEEE 48th Annual International Symposium on Computer Architecture (ISCA), 2021, Acceptance Rate: 18%
- Rasool Sharifi and Ashish Venkat, "CHEx86: Context-Sensitive Enforcement of Memory Safety via Microcode-Enabled Capabilities," in 2020 ACM/IEEE 47th Annual International Symposium on Computer Architecture (ISCA), 2020, Acceptance Rate: 18%, Top Pick in Hardware and Embedded Security Selected from Architecture/Security/VLSI Design Conferences Held Between 2015-2020!
- Lingxi Wu, Rasool Sharifi, Kevin Skadron, and Ashish Venkat, "DRAM-CAM: General-Purpose Bit-Serial Exact Pattern Matching," in IEEE Computer Architecture Letters (CAL), 2022
- Ali Jahanshahi, Rasool Sharifi, Mohammadreza Rezvani, and Hadi Zamani, "Inf4Edge: Automatic Resource-aware Generation of Energyefficient CNN Inference Accelerator for Edge Embedded FPGAs," in 2021 IEEE Workshop on Energy-Efficient Machine Learning (E2ML), 2021
- Rasool Sharifi and Zain Navabi, "Online Profiling for cluster-specific variable rate refreshing in high-density DRAM systems," in 2017 22nd IEEE European Test Symposium (ETS), 2017

Awards

CHEx86: Context-Sensitive Enforcement of Memory Safety via Microcode-Enabled Capabilities

Dec. 2021

Top Pick in Hardware and Embedded Security

Selected from Architecture/Security/VLSI Design Conferences Held Between 2015-2020

Skills

Programming Languages/Frameworks:

• C/C++, LLVM, MLIR, Python, PyTroch, JAX

Immigration Status and References

US permanent resident. Two references will be made available upon request.